The ideal is quality and quantity,
but face it, you're only human.
This is higher ed.
Hot takes.
And I'm Joel Goodman.
Work smarter, not harder.
This old adage has helped
many of us do our jobs better.
If you're an oldie, maybe that
meant setting up macros in your
word processor for actions that
you needed to repeat all the time.
Maybe it meant setting up labels and
folders in your email inbox and using
rules to sort incoming messages.
Or maybe it's using tools like
Zapier to automate different tasks.
Efficiency saves us a lot of time
In a bakery or factory, being
efficient with motion can reduce
strain and toll on your body.
In digital work, you can prevent carpal
tunnel or even feel a little more
superhuman with some productivity hacks.
Efficiency is good then, and it's
helped the world accomplish a lot.
Episode over what?
What was I talking about?
Uh, so there's a dark side to creating
all this extra time Efficiency
has an insatiable hunger for time.
Anytime saved has to be filled with
more production, and then you have to
make that production more efficient.
It's a terrible cycle and it's
bad, just really, really bad.
In higher ed, this shows its
face as doing more with less.
Uh, you've heard it, I've heard it.
If we're honest, you're probably
living it three or four times
over at this point, and the only
answer is to be more efficient.
The problem is that you've exhausted
all of the productivity hacks and
don't have any more time outside
of what are supposed to be normal
work hours to get more stuff done.
In 2025, the answer is ai.
I'm sorry.
That's ridiculous.
And I know it's being sold to
you that way, but it's a lie.
See, there's a point where efficiency
just produces diminishing returns,
especially in a field where quality is
all that differentiates your institution
from the one down the street I.
We've been so distracted by the shiny AI
marketing, sales pitches, and addictive
product design that we let a lot of
really bad, sometimes awful output slide.
I hear more and more often how marketing
professionals are using chat, GPT, the
most popular LLM product, serving the
most general range of people trained on
the most mainstream available content.
And they're using it
to do writing for them.
And I'm just gonna pause it.
This question, if you take an objective
step back, is the quality of that
output as good or better than content?
You used to write the old fashioned way.
I. Follow up question.
Do you believe that a predictive text
model trained on the lowest common
denominator of content is capable of
stringing together some words that will be
effective in a highly competitive market?
Here's the hard truth.
Quality performs better than quantity.
There's no point adding to the slop unless
you have no intention of standing out.
AI generated ad imagery.
It underperforms compared to
carefully design campaigns.
AI generated content typically has
to be rewritten multiple times.
AI built code will do not get me started.
Creative work is inefficient and
inefficiency produces better quality.
Doing more with less is never as
good as doing better with less.
When efficiency is chased at all
costs, we end up misplacing quality.
We end up promoting sloppy work producing
literal slop, and that hurts our brands
and our students and our people in
competitive fields like higher ed.
And I know I've said this
before, but our people are all
we have that differentiates us.
To compete, we have to
stop playing to the mean.
And to do that, we have to reclaim
our core human characteristics.
Quality comes from allocating time to
the right processes, Taking the time to
listen process, consider, and then apply
what we know might be less efficient
than asking an LLM to generate an idea.
But nine times outta 10, it is going
to produce better, more original
thought than that model will.
Here's something else
to think about today.
In 2025, the quote Doge model
of government overhaul is
being bandied about globally.
Ostensibly, this is about
increasing government efficiency,
but it also ignores the fact that
government is inefficient by design.
Democracy and public participation
in government have to be inefficient.
Total efficiency means no participation,
no questioning, no auditing, no new
ideas, no buy-in for the people.
This is the core of my argument today.
There's a point when the quest
for efficiency cancels out any
sense of art or creativity.
There's no thinking or considering or
challenging when we outsource to machines,
the very spark that makes us human.
So consider closely the things
that you choose to automate.
Make sure you aren't passing the things
that need your unique take on them.
Over to software.
Don't fall into the trap of thinking
that just because an LLM can mimic
your writing style, that it's
good enough for rock and roll.
It's only low quality simulacra.
It's soulless, lacking all aura, and
you deserve better than to have a cheap
knockoff of your own brilliance out in
the world masquerading as the real thing.
Have I convinced you yet?
I know I probably haven't,
so let me try one more thing.
We only have so many pieces
of our humanity to give away
before we lose it entirely.
What happens when, for efficiency's
sake, we forget how to write, how to
code, how to design, how to tell stories.
What happens when our core creative
spark is completely mediated by
LLMs generative models and the huge
corporations serving their bottom lines?
There's an argument
floating around the AI boom.
Law isn't going to take people's jobs.
It's just going to change them.
And I agree.
The AI boom makes us worse at our
jobs, makes our work more generic,
and encourages us to forget the
things that make us unique in
favor of conformity and hegemony.
Quality is inefficient.
Craft is inefficient.
Brilliance is inefficient.
Art is messy and inefficient.
Let's face it.
Humans are inefficient and
that's a beautiful thing.
Thanks for listening.
Connect with me Joel Goodman on Blue Sky.
LinkedIn got direct links
at higher ed Hot takes.com.